Scovell Family Papers, 1780-1847
Connecticut Historical Society
Scovell Family Papers
1780-1847
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Scovell family
1 linear foot (2 boxes)
Biographical Sketch
Noah Scovell was born in 1759 in Potapogue Parish, Saybrook, Connecticut, the son of William and Ruth Webb Scovell. Noah married Desire Pratt (1759-1819) of Essex and they raised five children, namely Noah (b. 1781), Lewis (1783-1806), Sebra or Seabury (1785-1805), Amos (1787-1852) and Maria (1789-1834). Noah was a merchant and shipbuilder. His vessels primarily traded in the West Indies and along the Eastern seaboard. They included the Maria (Sloop), Peggy (Brig), Nancy (Ship), Patty and Julia (Ship) and Manufacture (Brig). Between 1810-1812, he and his son Noah experimented with importing Merino sheep from Spain. Son Noah moved to New York to carry on the merchant trade and assist his father.
The elder Noah Scovell’s siblings were William, Matthew (1743-1805), Ezra (1748-1824) who lived in Berlin, Connecticut, and Dan (1752-1781), a resident of Colchester.
Scope and Content
The dealer from whom the collection was purchased organized the papers by subject. That arrangement has been changed to more nearly reflect the individuals and vessels central to the collection. The two Noah Scovell’s were both called “Captain” at various times, so there may be occasions when correspondence has been assigned to the wrong individual. It was also impossible to separate business from personal correspondence. As a result, the correspondence has only been divided into incoming and outgoing, then by date.
Business correspondence and ships papers comprise the bulk of the collection. The letters of Noah and Noah Jr. are arranged first in the collection, followed by missives written by or to other family members. Legal papers, financial records and ships’ papers cover the activities of both men and no attempt was made to distinguish between them.
Noah Scovell, Sr., wrote letters to his ship captains, including his son Noah, with instructions for selling cargo. Epaphroditus Champion invested in Scovell’s ships and was a frequent correspondent. According to his letters, Noah’s brother Ezra shipped meats and other goods on Noah’s vessels. James Arden, based in New York City, frequently informed Noah about the ships entering and leaving port. Other correspondents included Judson Canfield, Amos Peck and Nathaniel Ingraham, another New York City merchant. Among son Noah’s correspondence are reports from Spain about the type and number of Merino sheep being loaded aboard various ships, 1810-1812. As with his father, Noah Scovell Jr.’s correspondence is primarily business related. He wrote one letter in 1806 commiserating with his parents on the loss of their son, his brother, Lewis.
Amos Scovell wrote a mix of personal and business letters to his brother Noah Jr., 1805-1808. Noah Sr. appears to have been executor of his brother Dan’s estate and guardian of his son, Dan, according to papers, 1780-1792 filed under Dan Scovell. Noah’s son Lewis wrote to his father from Major Rufus Hitchcock’s house in Cheshire, 1798, and in 1805 kept brother Noah apprised of the health of their brother Seabury. Business and personal topics were mixed in Seabury’s letters to his father and brothers, 1798-1805.
Legal records of both son and father Noah, 1785-1810, consist of an apprenticeship agreement to teach John Williams Jr. how to be a mariner, 1785, an agreement between Amos Peck and Noah Scovell to keep Noah’s mother, 1795, summonses, an agreement between the master and fishermen of the Sloop Girl, 1805, and estate papers, 1801-1822.
Assorted business and personal financial records, namely bills, receipts, orders of payment, promissory notes and accounts, are arranged chronologically from 1784-1847. Medical bills, correspondence and “recipes” were separated by the dealer and remain so in this organization. They are also arranged chronologically, 1782-1829.
Ships’ papers include customs documents (many in a foreign language), lumber inspections, bills of exchange, accounts, bills and invoices, and correspondence. Where possible, the papers were arranged by name of vessel and the vessels are organized alphabetically. Of particular note is the contract for building the Peacock (Ship), and a sailor’s brief journal of his voyages aboard Scovell’s vessels.
The final folder in the collection contains the correspondence and notes of Reverend B. F. Case who at one time appears to have owned or at least had access to this collection.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Scovell, Noah, 1759-1821.; Scovell, Noah, b. 1781.
Family Names
Scovell family.
Subjects
Dolphin (Brig).; Nancy (Ship).; Patty and Julia (Ship).; Peacock (Brig).; Peggy (Brig).
Contents:
- Papers
  - Noah Scovell Sr. incoming correspondence, 1784-1793 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. incoming correspondence, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. incoming correspondence, 1795-1796 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. incoming correspondence, 1797-1799 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. incoming correspondence, 1800-1802 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. incoming correspondence, 1803-1806 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. incoming correspondence, 1808-1810 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. incoming correspondence, 1811-1817, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. incoming correspondence from Judson Canfield, 1805-1818 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. incoming correspondence from Amos Peck, 1798-1811 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. incoming correspondence from Ezra Scovell, 1786-1811 (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. outgoing correspondence, 1794-1820 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. outgoing correspondence to Noah Scovell Jr., 1798-1819 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Noah Scovell Jr. Incoming correspondence, 1796-1802 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Noah Scovell Jr. Incoming correspondence, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Noah Scovell Jr. Incoming correspondence, 1805-1807 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Noah Scovell Jr. Incoming correspondence, 1808-1810 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Noah Scovell Jr. Incoming correspondence, 1811-1825, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Noah Scovell Jr. outgoing correspondence, 1798-1829, undated (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Noah Scovell Jr. outgoing correspondence to Noah Scovell Sr., 1799-1829 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Amos Scovell correspondence and bills, 1805-1819, 1807, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Dan Scovell papers, 1780-1797, undated (Box 1, Folder 28-30)
  - Lewis Scovell correspondence, 1798-1805 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Seabury Scovell correspondence, 1798-1805 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Noah Scovell Sr. and Jr. legal records, 1785-1822 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Financial records, 1784-1847, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-17)
  - Tax lists and receipts, 1797-1804 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Medical bills, 1782-1829, undated (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
  - Medical recipes, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Lumber inspections, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Customs documents, 1790-1819 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Bills of exchange, 1793-1819 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Ships’ papers, 1785-1819, undated (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Ships’ papers, Dolphin (Brig), 1786-1789 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Ships’ papers, Gallant (Schooner), 1797-1798 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Ships’ papers, Maria (Sloop), 1790 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Ship’s papers, Manufacture (Brig), 1811 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ships’ papers, Nancy (Ship), 1794 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Ships’ papers, Patty & Julia (Ship), 1792-1794 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Ships’ papers, Peacock (Brig), 1790-1801 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Ships’ papers, Peggy (Brig), 1793-1796, undated (Box 2, Folder 35-37)
  - Unidentified materials (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Rev. B. F. Case correspondence and genealogical notes, 1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)